Guide to the Hulst family collection ARC.135
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hulst family collection
1702-circa 1950
1702-1878
Brooklyn Historical Society
Holsaert, Anthony
Hulst family
Fardon, Jacob
Hulst, William P.
Hulst, John P.
ARC.135
0.25 Linear Feet in one manuscript box, one oversize flat box, and two boxes of images by format.
The Hulst family collection relates primarily to the Hulst family in Brooklyn. The bulk of the materials in this collection were created between 1702 and 1878, though there are some documents from the mid-twentieth century. A good portion of the collection contains genealogical notes on the Hulst, Rider, and Van Duyn families; the remaining papers consist of deeds, bonds, correspondence, and receipts. Other document types in this collection include a copy book, an autograph poetry book, and photographs of family members and graves. An enslaved person bill of sale and a New Utrecht list of enslaved people and chimbles (chimneys) are also located in this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Hulst family papers were the gift of Miss Alletta M. Crump of Brooklyn, New York, in four accessions from 1960-1964.
Biographical / Historical
The Hulsts were a recognized Long Island family whose lineage in Brooklyn, New York began when Jacobus Van der Hulst of Vlissingen, Holland married Maria Bennett of Gowanus, Long Island, in 1679. The family name was shortened to "Hulst" upon the birth of their three children, John, Anthony, and Benjamin. Anthony Hulst (d. 1732) may have gone by one or a number of different last names, including Hulst, Holst, Holsaer, or Holsaert. The Hulsts resided in parts of Gowanus and New Utrecht, Long Island; later generations also moved north to Norfolk, New York, and John P. Hulst to Richmond, Virginia. Throughout the 18th and 19th centuries the Hulsts married into the Van Duyn, Luyster, Rider, and Bennet families.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by last name. Contents in individual folders are in chronological order. Material with a designation of Box 2 is stored in an oversize flat box. Daguerreotypes and a carte-de-visite are also boxed separately, with like material from other collections.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection is comprised of miscellaneous family and business records pertaining primarily to the Hulst and Van Duyn families. Deeds, indentures, receipts, correspondence, an estate inventory, and family records are among the majority of document types in this collection. Correspondents include Anthony Hulst (Holsaert), Maria Hulst, William P. Hulst, and John P. Hulst. Correspondence to Anthony Holsaert from John Griggs consists of an order for shoes to be made, with foot size marked off on the document. One correspondence from John P. Hulst's includes a hand-drawn image of, and commentary on Anthony Hulst, as well as commentary on the Northern railroad labor strife of 1877.
The deeds in this collection are to Jacob Fardon for land in Gowanus (1702), Peter Hulst of Newtown (1837), Anthony Holsaert (1704-1705), and Jacob Fardon in Brooklyn (1717). Other document types include an autograph poetry book of Sarah M. Hulst, a copybook of John P. Hulst, a printed Hymn by Margaret Gardiner and George D. Hulst, an enslaved person bill of sale to Johannes Holsaert from Gerritt Onckelbag (1728), and a New Utrecht tax list of enslaved people and chimbles (1709). There are extensive typed and handwritten genealogical notes on the Hulst family into the mid-twentieth century, and fragments of family records for the Rider, Holsaert-Bennet (Dutch), and Van Duyn families. The collection also includes three daguerreotypes (John P., Magdalena, and Jane Rider Hulst), a carte-de-visite of John P. Hulst, and photographs of family tombstones at the New Lots and Cypress Hills Cemeteries.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Materials
Hulst family papers, 1708-1824, Kroch Library, Cornell University.
Enslaved people -- bills of sale; Sepulchral monuments -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Bills of sale; Newtown (Queens County, N.Y.); Poetry; Deeds; Correspondence; Genealogy; Autograph albums; Photograph albums; Kings County (N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Gowanus (New York, N.Y.); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Estate inventories; Indentures; Hulst, Anthony, Sr.; Hulst, Anthony, Jr.; Van Duyn family; Rider family; Hulst family; Hulst, William P.; Hulst, John P.
- Buys, Jacob Janse, Deed to Jacob Fardon for land in Gowanus., 1702 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fardon, Yacop, 2 receipts to Rutgert Van Brunt and Willem Van Nuys for Bonds., 1724 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 2)
- Griggs, John, Correspondence to Anthony Holsaert., 1723 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 3)
- Holsaert, Antoni, Bond to Cornelis Van Duyn, Jr., 1751 (Box OS-32, Folder 1)
- Holsaert-Bennet Family Record., 1729-1749 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hulst Family Genealogical Notes., circa 1950 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hulst Family, Photographs of Family Graves., circa 1940s-1958 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hulst Family Daguerreotypes, circa 1850s; DAG.08-10 (Box Daguerreotypes 3)
- Hulst Family Scrapbook., 1846-1927 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hulst, George D. and Margaret Gardiner, Printed Hymn., 1930 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hulst, John P. (1823-1878), Correspondence., 1877-1878 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hulst, John P., Copybook., 1840-1841 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hulst, John P., carte-de-visite, circa 1870 (Box Cartes de Visite 1, Folder 1)
- Hulst, Maria, Inventory of her Estate., 1830 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hulst, Sarah M., Autograph Poetry Book., 1837-1838 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hulst, William B., Correspondence., 1866 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 13)
- Luyster, John, Correspondence To Maria Hulst., 1817 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 14)
- New Utrecht List of Slaves and Chimbles., 1709 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 15)
- Onckelbag, Gerritt, Slave Bill of Sale to Johannis Holsart., 1728 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 16)
- Remsen, Abraham A., Deed to Peter Hulst of Newtown., 1837 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 17)
- Rider Family Record, 1767-1813, circa 1815 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 18)
- Swaert, Johannes, Bill to Anthony Holsaert., 1717 (Box OS-32, Folder 1)
- Van Antwerp, Jacobus, Bill to Anthony Hulst (1727-1817)., 1772 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 19)
- Van Cleef, Cornelius, Deed to Anthony Holsaert., 1704-1705 (Box OS-32, Folder 1)
- Van Duyn Family Record., 1727-1737 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 20)
- Yorise, Rem, Deed to Jacob Fardon., 1717 (Box ARC.150 Box 1; ARC.135 Box 1, Folder 21)